<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning for Israel in a sermon preached at Christ-Church, in Dublin, the 30. of October, 1625. By Henry Leslie, one of his Majesties chaplaines in ordinary.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838155</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 805:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning for Israel in a sermon preached at Christ-Church, in Dublin, the 30. of October, 1625. By Henry Leslie, one of his Majesties chaplaines in ordinary.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Societie of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2518:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2518:1"/>
            <p>A WARNING For Iſrael, <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT CHRIST-CHVRCH, IN Dublin, the 30. of October, 1625.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Leſlie,</hi> one of his Majeſties Chaplaines in Ordinary.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERB. 22.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A prudent man foreſeeth the evill &amp; hideth himſelfe, but the fooliſh goe on ſtill and are puniſhed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE. 19.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O if thou haddest even knowne, at the leaſt in this thy day, thoſe things which belong unto thy peace!</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at Dublin by the Societie of STATIONERS, <hi>Anno</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2518:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, HENRY, LORD VISCOVNT FALKLAND Lord Deputie generall of the Kingdome of IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Neyther as valewing your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or abilitie, preſent this before your Honour; but your goodneſſe and vertue: not that I thinke the ſubject unfit your conſideration, but becauſe I am iealous of the compiler. Yet my preſumption is not great; for what I now doe, is obedience, yea but ſeconding in action, what your Honour thought worthy to be effected. Diſcourſes of this nature have not many Patrons: and to ſee great men buſie both their ſenſes with Divinitie, is <hi>mirum in terris.</hi> Yet the Church hath had a <hi>Sergius Paulus,</hi> a prudent Deputy, and a <hi>Publius</hi> alſo, from whom our Apostle might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive incouragement: and we have not loſt, but changed our late learned King, that mixed his meales with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb facs="tcp:2518:3"/>thoughts, and taught his Nobles the like wiſedome: and herein I know not whether we can judge him more happy in his Princely power, or Prieſtly prudence. That path that honoured him a King, may crowne you a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Neyther doe I provoke you by the father, as if there were nothing imitable in the ſonne; for who doth not ſee freſhly budding in his ſacred perſon, what his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſented to us in full eare? And your glory will be no leſſe in imitating his graces, then in preſenting his perſon.</p>
            <p>This (whatſoever it is) I place at your Lordſhips feet, if it pleaſe you, as well publiſhed as preſented, I have my deſire: but if it fayle herein, I ſhall not want to rejoyce that it once gave content. God adde to your dayes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and graces, and make you a true profeſſor of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Church in this kingdome; as alſo that your Lordſhip may long remaine with us a firme columne for the upholding the peace and tranquilitie of this State. For which, (with the reſt of your true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norers) I ſhall ever pray.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all duty and ſervice HENRY LESLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2518:3"/>
            <head>A VVARNING FOR <hi>JSRAEL.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HOSHA 14. VERS. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O Iſrael, returne unto the Lord thy God; for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the ordinary method of the Prophets, firſt to threaten, and then to comfort; firſt to denounce Gods judgements, and after to promiſe mercie and forgiveneſſe: And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the Prophet Hoſea in this 14. Chapter (which is a bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viary, and compend of the whole prophecie) begins with a threatning in the former verſe, <hi>Samaria ſhall become de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate; for ſhee hath rebelled againſt her God: they ſhall fall by the ſword, their Infants ſhall bee daſhed into peeces, and their women with childe ſhall bee ript up.</hi> And after in the <hi>fift verſe,</hi> there followeth a promiſe: <hi>I will heale their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, I will love them freely, for mine anger is turned away from him.</hi> What can bee the cauſe of ſuch a ſuddaine change? Iudgement is preſently turned into mercie: and the reaſon is, becauſe the threatnings, and the promiſes of God in Scripture are conditionall. The threatning in the former verſe is conditionall; <hi>Samariaſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate</hi> (namely) unleſſe ſhe repent. The promiſe likewiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2518:4"/>
               <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. is conditionall; <hi>I will heale their rebellion</hi> (namely) if ſo be they doe repent: and therefore between the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the promiſe, there is interlaced an exhortation to repentance, <hi>O Iſrael, returne unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where conſider with me, firſt the exhortation it ſelfe, [<hi>O Iſrael returne unto the Lord</hi>] &amp; then the arguments to inforce this exhortation, which are two; one taken from Gods mercy. [<hi>Hee is thy God</hi>] another taken from their owne miſery [<hi>for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</hi>] Againe in the exhortation, conſider firſt, the people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, [<hi>O Iſrael</hi>] &amp; then the dutie required; [<hi>Returne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord.</hi>] <hi>O Iſrael returne unto the Lord they God, for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The people exhorted, is <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereby wee may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, eyther the ten Tribes who made defection from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> following after <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> againſt whom the judgement is denounced in the former <hi>verſe:</hi> under the name of <hi>Samaria,</hi> becauſe <hi>Samaria</hi> was the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan Citie of that kingdome: or elſe by <hi>Iſrael</hi> wee may underſtand that <hi>Iſrael</hi> which was in the land of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for theſe two Tribes of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> are often called <hi>Iſrael</hi> by a <hi>Synecdoche.</hi> If by <hi>Iſrael</hi> we underſtand the tenne Tribes, againſt whom the judgement was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then it miniſters unto us theſe two inſtructions. Firſt, that Gods threatnings in Scripture are conditionall, for in the former <hi>verſe,</hi> deſolation is threatned againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and yet heere he exhorts <hi>Iſrael</hi> to repentance, that ſo ſhee might prevent that deſolation. Now unleſſe in the threatning <hi>Samaria ſhal be deſolate,</hi> there were underſtood this condition, except ſhe repent; the ſubſequent exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were in vaine: and indeede it is a certaine rule ſet downe by God himſelfe, <hi>When I have ſpoken againſt a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2518:4"/>to destroy them, and to reote them out: If they repent of their ſinnes, I will repent of the evill I thought to bring upon them:</hi> &amp; againe, <hi>If the wicked will returne from all his ſins, he ſhall ſurely live &amp; ſhall not die.</hi> Hence it is that God many times ſeemes to repeale his ſentence, according to that of <hi>Gregory. Nevit Deus aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do mutare se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit mutare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> he changes his ſentence, not his purpoſe: It was Gods ſentence againſt <hi>Nineveh, Yet fortie dayes,
<note place="margin">Ionah, 3 4.</note> &amp; Nineveh ſhall be destroyed.</hi> It was Gods ſentence to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Put thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die, and not live:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 38 1.</note> and yet neyther of theſe came to paſſe at that time. Doth this argue any inconſtancie in God, or want of power that hee could not performe what hee had ſpoken? No,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 23 19.</note> God forbid; <hi>God is not as man that he ſhould lye, neyther as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent: Hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not doe it? Hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it? I am the Lord and change not;</hi> Mal. 3.6. <hi>My counſell ſhall stand, and my will ſhalbe done, Iſa. 46.10.</hi> But the reaſon is, becauſe all the threatnings of God are conditionall, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the condition be not expreſſed. God ſaid to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech, Thou ſhalt die, becauſe of the woman which thou hast taken, Gen. 20.3.</hi> This would ſeeme an abſolute ſentence; yet was it onely conditionall, for God ſaith unto him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine verſ. 7. <hi>Deliver the man his wife, if not, thou ſhalt die.</hi> Thus the condition ſometimes is expreſſed, and alwaies is to be underſtood, according to that generall rule, <hi>Ierem. 18.7.8. So fortie dayes and Nineveh ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> the condition is to be underſtood, except they repent. <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah ſhall die:</hi> The condition is underſtood, unleſſe hee ſue unto God by prayer for a prorogation of his life. Now the condition being performed, the ſentence was voyde. So heere, <hi>Samaria ſhall be deſolate,</hi> a condition muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, unleſſe ſhee repent; otherwiſe, to what purpoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2518:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>were this exhortation, <hi>O Iſrael, returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, hence we learne that God gives warning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he puniſh. <hi>Samaria</hi> muſt become deſolate, but firſt the Lord muſt ſend vnto them, and forewarne them by the mouth of a Prophet, of that deſolation, exhorting them to prevent it by repentance; that ſo they might be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all excuſe. He gave warning to the old world by his ſervant <hi>Noah,</hi> a preacher of righteouſneſſe; to <hi>Sodome</hi> by <hi>Lot;</hi> to the <hi>Iewes</hi> by the <hi>Prophets</hi> that lived before the captivitie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem</hi> 35.15.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſent unto them all his ſervants the Prophets riſing up earely, and ſaying, returne now every man from his evill way, &amp; amend your works.</hi> Finally, hee gave warning to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> before her deſtruction by his owne Sonne, proteſting of his deſire to reclayme them. <hi>Ieruſalem, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem; How often would I have gathered thy children, as the Henne gathereth her chickins under her wings, and yee would not? Behold your habitation ſhalbe left deſolate.</hi> So he gives us watning at this time of an evill to come upon us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa</hi> 221 12.</note> Even, <hi>In this day dath the Lord God of heaſtes, call to weeping, and mourning, to baldeneſſe, and girding with ſackcloth.</hi> There is a threefold call to give us warning; one occaſionall, our ſinnes; another reall, Gods judgements already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; a third vocall, the admonitions of Gods faithfull ſervants. Gods wrath in Scripture is compared to fire: and as a fire is knowne, eyther by the ſmoake (as a ſigne alwayes accompanying fire) or by the flames breaking forth, or by the relation of others: So may Gods wrath now be knowne by ſuch three things. Firſt, by the great ſinnes of the land as a ſigne, or rather cauſe of Gods wrath, and a moſt certaine fore-runner, and fore warner of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deſtruction. For it is a generall rule ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both by Scripture and experience, that whereſoever ſin doth raigne, there Gods wrath is imminent; but ſinne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2518:5"/>raigneth in this land (I dare ſay, in no place more) without controlment. Wee have exceeded, not onely <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but alſo <hi>Sodome</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> in all their abominations. Now,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5 9.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I not viſit for theſe things ſaith the Lord? Or ſhall not my ſoule be avenged on ſuch a nation as this?</hi> Yea ſure, hee muſt viſit; If oppreſsion and ſactiledge; If Idolatrie and want of the knowledge of God; If inceſt and innocent bloud; If briberie and extortion; If neglect of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and fatherleſſe; If oathes and perjurie; If drunkeneſſe and gluttony; If pride, avarice and ambition; If fraud and robbery; If prophanation of the Sabboth, and contempt of Gods word, worſhip and ſervants: Finally, If all theſe, committed commonly in everie place, openly in the ſight of the Sunne, and ſafely without puniſhment, can draw downe the judgements of God upon a nation, then how ſhall it be poſsible for us to eſcape? Thus our ſinnes give us warning of Gods judgements. Secondly, the flames of this fire doe already breake out, and theſe beginnings of Gods judgements give us warning of a greater deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for when God takes a people in hand for to ſchoole them, he will eyther mend them, or end them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he begins with milde chaſtiſments (but if theſe doe not prevaile) he proceedes to ſharper corrections. In the 5. Chap. of <hi>Hoſea</hi> verſ. 12. he threatneth a gentle correction: <hi>I will be unto Ephraim as a Moath,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> &amp; unto the houſe of Iudah as a rettenneſſe.</hi> But this did no good, they were not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſlow gnawing of a ſmall moath: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee threatneth a heavier judgement. verſ. 14.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ</hi> 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>I will be unto Ephraim as a Lyon, and as a young Lyon to the houſe of Iudah.</hi> And Levit. 26. hee threatneth ſeverall plagues againſt the tranſgreſſors of his law: firſt ſickeneſſe, verſ. 16. then famine: verſ. 19.20. after that, deſtruction of their Cattle, verſ. 22. and after that, the ſword verſ. 25. and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2518:6"/>the peſtilence <hi>ibid:</hi> And after each judgement he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; <hi>And if yee will not yet for all this obey mee, but walke stubburnely againſt mee, I will bring ſeven times more plagues upon you.</hi> So now the Lord hath begun theſe yeares paſt to viſit us with famine, with death and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie; theſe are but the beginnings of evill: and unleſſe we repent, he hath heavier judgements in ſtore for us, he will even take his three ſtringed whippe in his hand, which will pierce our skinne, were it never ſo thicke. This is the ſecond warning Thirdly, there is yet a third, by the voyce of the Prophets, calling unto you, that unleſſe yee repent, yee ſhall die in your ſinnes. We have not now Prophets immediately inſpired by the holy Spirit to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell things to come, theſe were for the infancie of the Church, now the Church being built, God will have it governed by ordinary Paſtors: but we have Prophets for expounding of the Law, that can foretell you of Gods judgements, by infallible conſequence out of Gods word, and by application of theſe threatnings which they finde in the Law againſt impenitent ſinners after this manner: Who ſo perſevere in ſinnes, &amp; harden their hearts againſt all admonitions, ſhalbe overtaken with Gods judgements: but this people perſevere in their ſinnes, &amp;c. Thus ought wee to binde your ſinnes upon your conſciences, and if we doe not, your bloud will be required at our hands. Yee know what charge God gave vnto <hi>Ezechiel, Sonne of man I have made thee a watchman unto the houſe of Iſrael:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3 17.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heare the word at my mouth, and give them vvarning from me: When I ſhall ſay unto the wicked thou ſhalt ſurely die, and thou givest not him warning, the ſame wicked man ſhall die in his iniquitie; but his bloud will I require at thine hand. But if thou warne the wicked, and he turne not from his wickedneſſe, he ſhall die in his iniquitie, but thou hast de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2518:6"/>thy ſoule.</hi> The ſame charge lyeth upon theſe whom God now hath made watchmen unto the houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> for Chap. 33.2. the ſame dutie is required from ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Miniſters who receive their calling from men.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33 23.</note> 
               <hi>If the people of the land take a man from among them, and ſet him for their watchman, if when he ſeeth the ſword come upon the land, he blow the Trumpet and vvarne the people, then hee that will not be warned his bloud ſhall be upon his owne head, &amp;c.</hi> But as in the dayes of <hi>Ieremie</hi> there were lying Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that prophecied peace, when deſtruction was at hand; ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23.11.</note> that God would <hi>breake the yoke of Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar, within the ſpace of two yeares,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem</hi> 8.11</note> and ſo heale the burt of the people with ſweete wordes:</hi> So there are at this time that love to preach <hi>Placentia,</hi> and make Sermons, as the Poet did his fables, <hi>Populo ut placerent: Sowing pillowes under the elbowes of the wicked.</hi> The occaſion is, becauſe they ſeeke great things for themſelves, therefore doe they ſtudie to pleaſe men: for they ſee that <hi>Zedekiah</hi> will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, when <hi>Micajah</hi> will be ſent to priſon,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.</note> and fed with the bread of affliction:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>rem.</hi> 20.1.2.</note> and <hi>Paſhur</hi> will be a gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the houſe of the Lord, when the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> by his authoritie ſhall be put in the ſtockes.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 3.</note> For theſe are the times foretold by the Apoſtle, wherein the itching eares of men cannot abide wholſome doctrine, but <hi>They hate him that rebuketh in the gate,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10.</note> and they abhorre him that ſpeaketh uprightly:</hi> as <hi>Achab</hi> hated <hi>Micajah,</hi> becauſe he prophecied evill, that is, he faithfully warned him of that judgement which afterward came upon him. Wee are come to ſuch an height of iniquitie, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was when ſhee could not indure the the rebukes of eyther Prieſt or Prophet.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoj.</hi> 4.4</note> 
               <hi>Let none rebuke nor reprove another</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>for this people are as they that rebuke the Priest.</hi> And by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, They ſay unto the Seers, ſee not;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 39.10.</note> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2518:7"/>to the Prophets, prophecie not unto us right things, but ſpeake flattering things unto us.</hi> And <hi>Micah. 2.11. If a man will ſay, I will prophecie unto thee of Wine &amp; of ſtrong drinke</hi> (that is, if hee will tell them pleaſant tales) <hi>hee ſhall even be the Prophet of this people.</hi> But it behooveth us whom the Lord hath made watchmen over his Ieruſalem, if we will deliver our owne ſoules, and be free from the bloud of all men, to blow the Trumpet, and give warning to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Let us remember that caveat which the Lord gave unto <hi>Baruch.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 45.4.</note> Behold that which I have built, will I deſtroy, and that which I have planted, will I plucke up, even this whole land, and ſeckeſt thou great things for thyſelfe? Seeke them not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b 32 22.</note> And ſolet us ſay with <hi>Elihu, I know not to give flattering titles unto man; for in ſo doing my maker ſhould take me away ſuddainely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King</hi> 22.14.</note> Let us reſolve with <hi>Micajah, As the Lord liveth, whatſoever the Lord ſaith unto me, that will I ſpeake.</hi> Although <hi>Zedekiah</hi> doeſmite mee on the cheeke and <hi>Amaziah</hi> informe againſt mee to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and others diſwade mee from prophecying at <hi>Bethel,</hi> becauſe it is the Kings Court: yet for Sions ſake I will not hold my peace, but I will lift up my voyce like a Trumpet, and ſhew the people their ſinnes, and forewarne them of Gods judgements, crying, <hi>Samaria ſhall be deſolate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Iſrael returne unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, if by <hi>Iſrael,</hi> wee underſtand them of the land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> then yee ſhall obſerve from hence; That the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of other men, ſhould be our inſtructions; the judgements of God upon others, ſhould waken us up, and make us looke about us, to ſee whether or not we be in the like danger. If our neighbours houſe be on fire, it is time to looke to our owne: If <hi>Samaria</hi> become deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, then let that <hi>Iſrael</hi> which is in the land of <hi>Iudah</hi> take heede, leaſt, as they have beene partaker with her, in her
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2518:7"/>ſinnes, ſo they doe alſo receive of her plagues. Now I can tell you that <hi>Samaria</hi> is become deſolate: The wrath of God in a great meaſure hath ſeaſed upon our neighbor Nations, that they may take up the ſame lamentation that <hi>Ieremie</hi> did, <hi>The ſword devoureth abroad,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.20.</note> and death is at home.</hi> Even that famous Citie of <hi>London</hi> is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fearefull ſpectacle of Gods judgements: God hath met with her in the Moneth of her affliction. Men women and Children, fall downe in the ſtreeres, ſmitten, not with the ſword of the <hi>Aſsirians,</hi> that were ſent againſt <hi>Samaria,</hi> but by the ſword of the deſtroying Angell, that ſlew the <hi>Aſsirians:</hi> in a word, there is nothing but deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in her ſtreetes, <hi>Rachel</hi> mourning for her children, &amp; cannot be comforted. O Lord. What have they deſerved which wee have not? Were they more vile and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable then wee? No,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thinke not that thoſe eighteene upon whom the Tower of Siloam fell, and ſlew them, were greater ſinners then others: I tell you, nay; but except yee amend your liues, yee ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> What (I pray you) are the ſinnes for which it hath pleaſed God to enter into judgement with our neighbour Nation? Is it the pride and prodigalitie of England? Is it their drunkenneſſe, and gluttonie? Is it their luxurie and uncleanneſſe? Is it their oathes and oppreſsion? Or finally, Is it their contempt of Gods word and formall hypocriſie? Looke upon your ſelves with unpartiall eyes, and yee will finde, that wee have juſtified our ſiſter <hi>Samaria</hi> in all her abominations, that the Lord may juſtly take up againſt us the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint he doth againſt <hi>Iudah, Ierem. 3.8.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 3.8.</note> When backeſliding Iſrael committed adulterie, and I had put her away, and given her a Bill of divorce, yet her treacherous ſiſter Iudah feared not, but went and played the harlot alſo.</hi> What will follow hereupon, but as is <hi>Iſai. 10.12. Shall I not,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſal.</hi> 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as I have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2518:8"/>done unto Samaria and her Idoles, ſo doe to Ieruſalem and her Idols?</hi> But let the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> rather be <hi>Iudah,</hi> and this (where wee live) <hi>Samaria:</hi> and ſo the application will ſuite better. For yee know, <hi>Iudah</hi> was the firſt and the mother kingdome, ſo is England to us: <hi>Samaria</hi> was farre more corrupt in Religion then <hi>Iudah,</hi> having one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſhew of truth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. antiq. l. b. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> in Circumciſion, Temple, Prieſt, Books of <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſo is this Kingdome where we live. The <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes</hi> were a mixt people of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſo are wee heere.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.33.</note> The <hi>Samaritanes</hi> had a mixt worſhip; for in <hi>Samaria</hi> both the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Gods of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were worſhipped:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. antiq. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap. ult.</hi>
               </note> and would to God it were not ſo heere. Is there not in everie Towne, Village, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Kingdome, a mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> whereupon they bragge their Fathers to have worſhipped?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1, 20</note> Is there not a ſucceſſion of Prieſts ſacrificing upon everie mountaine, and under everie greene Tree? and (leaſt thus ſucceſſion ſhould fayle for want of iſſue, becauſe they have no wives of their owne.) Is there not a continuall ſupply every day from <hi>Rome?</hi> And finally, Are there not many Relickes of Saints, and holy Wels, of more worth (if yee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them) then <hi>Iacobs</hi> Well in <hi>Samaria?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4, 12. <hi>Ioſeph, antiq, lib,</hi> 11, <hi>cap,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> Beſides, <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> was a receptacle for all fugitive perſons who were not ſuffered to live at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for ſtrange wives, or for other crimes, for which cauſe their Temple was called <hi>Templum tranſgreſſorum:</hi> And what better is this of ours? Doe not all ſort of malectors flie hither as unto a Citie of refuge, who dare not live at home, ſome for ſtrange wives, ſome for bloud, ſome for theſt, and the beſt for debt;
<note place="margin">Ioſeph, antiq. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cap, vii,</note> making this land a verie denne of theeves? Laſtly, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reports that the <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> whenſoever the <hi>Iewes</hi> were in proſperitie, would be accounted <hi>Iewes;</hi> but when the <hi>Iewes</hi> were oppreſſed by their enemies, then they did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2518:8"/>diſclaime all affinitie with <hi>Iewes,</hi> as having their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie from <hi>Aſsiria,</hi> and joyned with their enemies: and, Is it not to be feared that we have ſuch fayned friends among us, that now profeſſe themſelves ſubjects to our Kings Majeſtie, none better, nor more deſirous of the peace of the Kingdome; who yet if the <hi>Aſsirians</hi> ſhould come againſt us, would prove our moſt dangerous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? If the <hi>Pope</hi> have their hearts, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> will have their ſervice. In all theſe reſpects may this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be called <hi>Samaria.</hi> Well then, Hath God begun to viſit <hi>Iudah?</hi> What ſhall become of <hi>Samaria?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, <hi>Pet,</hi> 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and if judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begin at Gods owne houſe What ſhall the end bee of them which obey not the Goſpell? If this bee done to the greene Tree, What ſhall become of the drie wood? If God ſpare not the naturall branches, How will he ſpare us who are but wilde Olives? Remember what God faith to the <hi>Iewes</hi> who ſojourned in the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had ſubdued <hi>Iudah,</hi> becauſe they were not affected with the evill that was to come upon their mother nation, <hi>Ierem.</hi> Chap. 44.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ,</hi> 3,</note> 
               <hi>Yee have ſeene all the evill that I have brought upon Ieruſalem, and upon all the Cities of Iudah, how they are deſolate becauſe of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe</hi> — yet they (namely that remaine in the land of <hi>Egipt) are not humbled unto this day,
<note place="margin">10</note> neyther have they feared — therefore thus ſaith the Lord of heastes,
<note place="margin">11</note> I will ſet my face against you — and I will viſit them that dvvell in the land of Egipt, as I have viſited Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">13</note> by the ſword, by the famine, and by the peſtilence.</hi> Now our caſe is juſt as theirs was. Wee ſojourne here in a land of darkeneſſe, like <hi>Egipt,</hi> and wee have ſeene what evill the Lord hath brought upon our mother nation, becauſe of their ſinnes, yet are not wee humbled unto this day, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have wee feared: What remayneth then? But that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2518:9"/>God viſit us, as hee hath done them? Therefore learne from the correction of your neighbours to returne unto the Lord in time, and make your peace with God. The puniſhments of the <hi>Iewes, are our enſamples</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) to the intent that <hi>Wee ſhould not lust after evill things,
<note place="margin">1, <hi>Cor,</hi> 10, 6</note> as they alſo lusted.</hi> The judgements of God upon our neighbours, ſhould be unto us as thoſe arrowes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Ionathan</hi> forewarned <hi>David</hi> of the Kings diſpleaſure: he ſhot not at him, but over and beyond him; yet <hi>David</hi> underſtood thereby that the King was angrie, and made haſt to be gone; ſo may wee perceive by theſe darts that come from heaven, and fall not upon us but neere unto us, that Gods wrath is kindled againſt us; and therefore wee ſhall doe well, to get up as <hi>David</hi> did, and make haſt to flie from the face of an angrie God, hiding our ſelves in the holes of that rocke CHRIST IESVS, who is a propitiation for our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverb.</hi> 22,3</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>A prudent man ſeeth the plague and hideth himſelfe.</hi> He <hi>ſeeth</hi> it in the Oracles of the Prophets, in the ſinnes of the people, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it is begun upon others, and <hi>he hideth himſelfe,</hi> that is, he prevents it by repentance, hee makes his peace with God, he hides himſelfe under the mantle of Chriſts righteouſneſſe; hee gets the dore-poſtes of his heart to be ſprinkled with the bloud of that immaculate Lambe, that ſo hee may bee ſafe from the hand of a deſtroying Angell in the day of the fierceneſſe of Gods wrath. God graunt unto us all this wiſedome to foreſee the plague, and hide our ſelves; for behold I give you warning, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> is become deſolate, therefore <hi>let Iſrael returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the people exhorted, I come to the dutie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which is, to returne unto the Lord. This phraſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> is a Metaphor drawen from travellers, who having loſt their way, muſt come backe againe and returne into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2518:9"/>the right way. Beloved, wee all are (or ſhould be) tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers to heaven, where out home is; but we have ſtrayed out of the way, and gone a quite contrarie courſe: wee are prodigall children that have departed from our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and gone into a farre countrie: wee are loſt ſheepe that have ſtraied from the fold.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſal.</hi> 53.6.</note> 
               <hi>All we like ſheepe have gone astray; vvee have turned every one to his one way.</hi> Wee have ſtrayed out of Gods paſtures, into Sathans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures; therefore wee muſt turne backe againe, and ſet our faces towards God, upon whom wee have turned out backes. The word is not ſimply to turne from one thing to another, but to returne, namely, to that which wee was before: implying three things. Firſt, that once they were with the Lord. Secondly, that they had gone away from him. Thirdly, that they muſt come home to him againe. This is true of all men. Wee were once with God, for being created after his image, wee had fellowſhip with God, and God with us. But wee did fall away from God, and became his enemies; for ſinne turnes and averts a mans ſoule from God, according to that of the Prophet, <hi>Your iniquities have ſeparated betweene you, and your God:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.</note> and your ſinnes have hid his face from you:</hi> And now unleſſe wee would periſh, it behooveth us to returne againe to him. But in a ſpeciall manner this agreeth to the people of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> They were Gods people, not onely by creation, but by particular adoption. The Lord did chuſe them above all the people of the earth, to ſet his love upon them; they were a holy people, a royall Nation, a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen generation, to the Lord their God: hee dealt not ſo with everie Nation, as with them; for he gave his Lawes unto <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his teſtimonies to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To them were committed the Oracles of God; to them did appertaine the adoption, and the glorie, and the covenants, and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2518:10"/>giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the promiſes, of them were the Fathers, and of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fleſh, CHRIST came. Yet ſuch was their ungratitude, that they did kicke up their heeles againſt the Lord their Maſter and Maker; they went away from him a whoring after their owne inventions: They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Idolatrie upon everie mountaine, and under everie greene Tree.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.13.</note> In a word, they forſooke the Lord the fountaine of living waters, and digged unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Ciſterns that could hold no water. And now here God by his judgements doth call them to returne againe unto him. <hi>O Iſrael, returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere (before I proceede any further) obſerve with mee, That humiliation goeth alwayes before grace, the ſenſe and apprehenſion of our owne wandring from God, is the onely way and meanes to bring us to God. <hi>Notitia peccati, initium ſalutis. The right understanding and true acknowledgement of our owne miſerie, is the firſt ſteppe to ſalvation:</hi> for if <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt returne to the Lord, then ſhe muſt be poſſeſſed with an opinion of her owne wandring from the Lord, ſhee muſt ſee that ſhee hath gone aſtray, and that there is no true comfort to be found in thoſe pathes of ſinne, in which ſhee walked. For, How can a man frame himſelfe to enter into a right courſe, till hee bee fully reſolved and perſwaded within himſelfe, that hee hath beene miſtaken in his former courſe of life? So the prodigall ſonne (a true patterne of a penitent ſinner) never ſeekes to his father, till that <hi>hee came to himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> then hee ſaw his error, and reſolved to returne to his father. The Prophet Chap. 5.15. bringeth in God, coupling theſe two together, <hi>Till they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their offence; and ſeeke my face:</hi> becauſe wee muſt firſt acknowledge our offence, before wee can ſeeke Gods
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2518:10"/>face, the full ſtomacke of a <hi>Phariſee</hi> will never thirſt to drinke of the cup of ſalvation:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.53.</note> onely the hungrie and the thirſtie; therefore God <hi>filleth the hungrie with good things, and ſendeth away the full emptie:</hi> You ſee who they are that CHRIST calleth to bee eaſed of their ſinnes; even the wearie and laden,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11 28.</note> 
               <hi>Come unto mee yee that are wearie and laden:</hi> that is, yee, who finde your conſciences to be laden with the burden of the Law, and the burden of ſinne and are ſo weary of theſe burdens, that they are grievous to you to beare. Such alſo bee they whom hee calleth ſinners, and ſicke. <hi>Matth. 9.12.13. The whole neede not a Phyſitian, but the ſicke, I am not come to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance.</hi> What? Is there any whole? Is there any righteous? No, indeed, all are ſinners, all are ſicke: but hee calleth onely thoſe ſinners and ſicke, who feele and acknowledge themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to be ſuch: as for the reſt whoſe eyes are not ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſee the miſerable eſtate wherein they ſtand by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he termes them righteous, and whole. Such are they whom he calleth loſt, <hi>Matth. 15.24.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 19.10.</note> I am ſent but unto the lost ſheepe,</hi> that is, unto ſuch as are loſt in their owne opinion: It is onely thoſe whom hee ſeeketh and ſaveth, as is well ſet forth in the Parables, <hi>of the loſt Sheepe, loſt Groate,</hi> and <hi>lost Childe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 15, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5 3.</note> Such alſo are they who are called poore: <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit,</hi> namely theſe who finde themſelves to abound with many inward wants: finally they are called fatherleſſe. In the fourth <hi>verſe</hi> of this Chap. <hi>With thee the fatherleſſe findeth mercie,</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, when as a man is brought to the ſtraights of a poore deſolate ſhiftleſſe Orphan, then is he a ſubject fit for mercie. So, that if wee would returne unto the Lord, firſt wee muſt ſee our ſtraying from the Lord: If wee would ſeeke Gods face, firſt wee muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2518:11"/>knowledge our offence: If wee would have God to fill us with good things, firſt wee muſt bee hungrie, even emptied of our evill liquor: If wee would have CHRIST to refreſh us with rivers of water, and flagons of wine; then wee muſt be thirſtie, that is, pained through the ſenſe of our want of ſpirituall drinke: If wee would have CHRIST to eaſe us of our burdens, firſt wee muſt bee wearie of them, that is, wee muſt feele our burdens to lye heavie upon us, and be grieved with the ſenſe of them: If wee would have the Saviour to ſave us, wee muſt bee ſinners, that is, humbled with the ſight and ſenſe of our ſinnes. If wee would have that great Phyſitian to cure us, wee muſt firſt be ſicke, that is, ſenſible of our diſeaſe, for he will not cure any of us, till firſt hee have launced our wounds unto the very bottome: If wee would have the good Sheepheard to finde us, wee muſt bee loſt in our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, even out of all hope of ſalvation in reſpect of anie thing that is in us. Finally, If wee would have the God of mercie to ſhew mercie unto us, then firſt wee muſt be fatherleſſe, that is, hopeleſſe and helpeleſſe in our ſelves. For hee is the <hi>God that reſiſteth the proud,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam. s.</hi> 5.</note> but giveth grace to the humble.</hi> Hereby then may a man judge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whether or no, hee bee in the way of ſalvation. Didſt thou never ſee thy wofull miſerie, and the wretched eſtate wherein thou art by reaſon of ſinne, how thou haſt turned thy backe upon God, and art out of his favour? Then haſt thou juſt cauſe to ſuſpect thy ſelfe, that thou haſt not yet entred at the ſtraight gate, to walke towards the Lord; for as there can be no birth without the paines of the travaile going before: ſo neyther any true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſion, without ſome terrours of the Law, and ſtraits of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The Infant that hath beene layd onely nine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, in the wombe of the mother, is not delivered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2518:11"/>paine, ſuppoſe ſhee conceived it with pleaſure: and Thinkeſt thou to part with ſinne, which in thee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with thee, and which ſince, ſo often thou haſt nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with pleaſure, and not to prove the dolours of the ſecond birth? No, not aſſuredly; there is the humbled ſoule, the wounded conſcience, the contrite ſpirit, the broken heart, the mourning weede, the melting eye, the pale countenance, the voyce of lamentation; theſe are the dolours of the ſecond birth, which wee meete with ſo ſoone as wee begin to returne to the Lord. On the other part, Haſt thou found in thy ſelfe theſe inward wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and humiliations? Haſt thou groaned under the burden of thy ſinne, and under the burden of Gods wrath? Haſt thou felt the terrours of God fighting againſt thee, and the invenomed arrowes of the Almightie ſticking faſt in thy ribbes? Then may thou conceive good hope that thou art in the way of ſalvation. If thou bee poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an opinion of thine owne wandring from the Lord; If thou be convicted that thou haſt ſtrayed from him: Then it is like thou wilt ſeeke to returne. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth God oftentimes call upon men to conſider their wayes, to call their lives to account, that ſo they may ſee how farre their ſoule is averted from God. <hi>Know thy ſinnes, O Ieruſalem, Iere.</hi> 3.13. The like ſpeech is uſed by the Prophet <hi>Zephanie, Fan your ſelves oh my people.</hi> Yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> doth oftentimes put us in minde of this dutie, <hi>Oh let us ſearch and trie our wayes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 3 20.</note> and turne unto the Lord.</hi> Firſt wee muſt ſearch our wayes, to finde out our owne wandrings, and then returne unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>And that yee may underſtand what is the dutie here required (becauſe this word <hi>Returne</hi> doth expreſſe a change, not of place, but of qualities) I will ſhew unto you. Firſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2518:12"/>from whence, Secondly to whom, Thirdly how wee muſt turne. As for the firſt wee muſt returne from our ſinnes: This is expreſſed <hi>Iſai</hi> 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his way in and the unrighteous his owne imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and returne unto the Lord.</hi> Let the wicked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his wayes, there is <hi>Terminus à quo.</hi> This turning from ſinne is called Mortification, and it contaynes five things. Firſt, a ſenſe and ſorrow for ſinne. Secondly, a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and deteſtation of ſinne. Thirdly, a purpoſe in minde to leave ſinne. Fourthly, an inclination in will to doe the ſame. Fiftly, an indeavour in life and converſation to forſake ſinne altogether. This muſt hee doe, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto the Lord: Firſt hee muſt bee caſt downe with a deepe ſight and ſenſe of his ſinne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 38.18.</note> ſaying with <hi>David, I agnize my ſinne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128.</note> and am ſorry for mine iniquite.</hi> He muſt hate and abhorre ſinne, as the greateſt evill in the world, ſaying with the ſame Prophet, <hi>Doe I not hate everie evill vvay.</hi> He muſt reſolve with himſelfe never to commit any ſinne. This muſt bee alſo the deſire of his heart, and the indeavour of his whole life. Otherwiſe, hee cannot returne unto the Lord, for God will not take a wicked man by the hand, nor have fellowſhip with the throne of iniquitie.</p>
            <p>Againe. To whom muſt wee turne? <hi>To the Lord,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that <hi>Ierem.</hi> 4.1. <hi>O Iſrael, if thou returne, returne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, ſaith the Lord;</hi> not to any other, not to my Angels, not to my Saints, not to my Martyres, not to my Mother; but to my owne ſelfe. In the 7. Chap verſ. 16. this people is accuſed that <hi>They did returne, but not to the moſt high.</hi> They had ſome beginning of repentance, but it fayled by the way, and brought them not ſo farre as home to the Lord. <hi>They were like a deceitfull bow,</hi> for, after all their aymes and offers of turning to the Lord; they ſtarted back,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2518:12"/>and returned not to the Lord, but to their Idols, they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their ſinnes as a Dogge to his vomite. It is not enough then to ceaſe from ſinne, but withall wee muſt turne unto the Lord; that is, wee muſt turne our hearts upward to heaven, ſetting our affections on things that are above; wee muſt fixe our eye upon God, and make towards him with the foote, walking in the way of his Commandements, that all men may ſee that wee are not of this world, but that our converſation is in heaven. This turning to the Lord, is called a riſing to newneſſe of life, and it hath three parts. Firſt, a reſolution in the minde. Secondly, a luſt in the will. Thirdly, an indeavour in life and converſation to obey God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh</hi> 24.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106.</note> Every man ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve as <hi>Ioſhua; I and myne houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> And as <hi>David, I have ſworne, and I will performe it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aeh,</hi> 13 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Act,</hi> 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that I will keepe thy righteous judgements.</hi> This muſt bee his deſire alſo, as it was <hi>Pauls,</hi> hee <hi>deſired to live honeſtly.</hi> Hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorted the <hi>Antiochians</hi> that <hi>with their heart they would cleave unto the Lord.</hi> And finally here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto muſt wee indeavour our ſelves throughout the whole courſe of our life. So did the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Act. 24.16.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6.</note> Herein I indeavour my ſelfe to have alway a cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God and towards Men.</hi> And <hi>David, I have a reſpect to all thy commandements.</hi> Whoſoever hath theſe, is turned from ſinne unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>The manner how wee muſt returne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.12.</note> is expreſſed by the Prophet <hi>Ioel. Turne unto me with all your heart, and with fasting, weeping, and mourning.</hi> Whence yee may obſerve foure properties of our converſion. Firſt, wee muſt turne with the heart, therefore our converſion muſt be volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: there is a reformation which is not voluntarie, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the will when a man turnes not from ſinne, but ſinne turnes from him: becauſe eyther hee cannot pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2518:13"/>it for want of ſtrength, or dare not for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Such a man may ſeeme to turne from ſinne, but it is not with his heart. Wee muſt turne with the heart, even ſo willingly, that it be our chiefe delight to uſe all meanes for to ſet forward this worke: for nothing is done well, but that which is done with the will. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, wee muſt turne, not onely with our heart, but <hi>with all our heart,</hi> therefore our converſion muſt be ſincere: for as in Scripture the Phraſes of <hi>a double heart,</hi> 1 Chron. 12.33. <hi>a devided heart,</hi> Hoſ. 10.2. <hi>A heart and a heart,</hi> Pſal. 12. a are uſed to ſignifie hypocriſie: So this phraſe, <hi>With all the heart,</hi> doth ſignifie ſinceritie. Then wee muſt turne unto the Lord <hi>with all our heart,</hi> that is to ſay, ſincerly, and not for ſhew onely: wee muſt draw neere unto God, not onely with the lips,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.6.</note> but with the heart alſo: for <hi>Hee loveth trueth in the inward affections.</hi> In this ſenſe it is ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> that hee <hi>followed God with all his heart,</hi> 1. King. 14.8. And of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that <hi>Hee turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoule, and with all his might. 2. King. 23.25.</hi> And of the people in the time of King <hi>Aſa,</hi> that the oath which they made before the Lord, was <hi>With all their heart,</hi> 2. Chron. 15.15. But <hi>Ierem. 3.10.</hi> The Lord accuſeth his people for want of this ſinceritie, <hi>Her rebellious ſister Iudah, hath not returned unto me with her whole heart, but faynedly.</hi> Thirdly, wee muſt turne <hi>with all our heart,</hi> therefore our converſion muſt be a thorow change of the whole man, of the whole life; though it be imperfect in degrees, yet it muſt be perfect in regard of parts. Wee muſt not halt betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Baal:</hi> Wee cannot ſerve both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mammon:</hi> God will not be content with a part of the heart; he will eyther have all, or none. It is ſaid of <hi>Iehu,</hi> that he did not walke in the Law of the Lord, <hi>with his whole heart,</hi> for why? Albeit hee obeyed God in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2518:13"/>ſome things, cutting off the houſe of <hi>Achab, Yet hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from the ſinne of Ieroboam, 2. King. 10.31.</hi> And ſo there be many that give but the halfe turne, like to <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> who was (not altogether, but) <hi>almoſt perſwaded to become a Christian.</hi> Some turning their wordes, not their deeds, as our verball profeſſors. And others againe turning from many ſinnes, and yet (with <hi>Herod</hi>) remaine untur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from one ſpeciall beloved ſinne. Theſe be but falſe turnings: our converſion muſt bee a thorow change, wee muſt turne <hi>with all our hearts.</hi> Finally, wee muſt turne not onely with all our hearts, but alſo <hi>with fasting, weeping, and mourning:</hi> therefore our converſion muſt not be inward onely; but it muſt bee expreſſed outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe things, wherein conſiſts the practiſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, namely, <hi>faſting, &amp;c.</hi> And that eſpecially in the time of any great affliction, ſuch as this was when the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> had foretold the people of the comming of the <hi>Chaldeans. Esther</hi> when ſhee heard of the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded deſtruction of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> appointed a faſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esth.</hi> 4 10. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.4. 2. <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 20 3, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Iudg</hi> 20, 26. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3.</note> So did <hi>Nehemiah</hi> when hee heard of the deſolation of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> when the <hi>Moabites</hi> came up againſt him: and <hi>David</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan</hi> were ſlaine: and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they were overthrowne by the <hi>Benjamites:</hi> and the <hi>Ninivites</hi> when deſtruction was threatened againſt them. And have wee not juſt cauſe to doe the like at this time? If wee conſider our grievous ſinnes, and the judgements of God which hang over our heads, together with the troubleſome eſtate of Gods Church in other places. Even this laſt may miniſter unto us ſufficient matter of griefe, though our owne private eſtate were never ſo peaceable. Godly <hi>Nehemiah</hi> being placed in the honourable ſervice of <hi>Artaſhaſhte,</hi> was not ſo much comforted at his owne good eſtate,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2518:14"/>as grieved at the deſolation of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nekem</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>King</hi> 19.4. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4 19.</note> Decay of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and increaſe of Idolatrie, made <hi>Elijah</hi> wearie of his life: The Arke of God captivated, and the glory de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> drave all comfort out of the heart of <hi>Phineas</hi> wife. Theſe (and many moe examples) teach us, That the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſhould bee the matter of our griefe. Caſt now but an eye upon the ruefull face of Chriſtendome; and yee will finde that it is time to <hi>Hang up our Harpes upon the Willowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137 2. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2 15.</note> and (as the Prophet cals us) to <hi>blow the Trumpet in Sion, and to ſanctifie a faſt:</hi> turning unto the Lord, <hi>with all our hearts, and with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, weeping, and mourning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But heere yee may aske mee the queſtion, Whether or not it be in our power to returne unto the Lord, ſince wee are exhorted thereunto? Anſwere, No, without a ſpeciall grace given us from above. The Scripture eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where hath diſabled us, pronouncing a man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be the <hi>Childe of wrath,</hi> Epheſ. 2.3. <hi>A tranſoreſſor from the wombe,</hi> Iſai. 48.8. <hi>Dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1. Coloſſ. 2.13. Wee are not onely ſicke with ſinne, or wounded by ſinne, or halfe dead, but ſtarke dead, bereft of all ſpirituall life, ſenſe, and motion. And therefore in our ſelves wee are <hi>of no ſtrength, Rom. 5.6.</hi> For our minde is darke, <hi>Epheſ. 5.8.</hi> Not perceiving the things of the ſpirit, 1. Cor. 2, 14. Our will perverſe, Gen. 6.5. Ierem. 17.9. The affections rebellious, <hi>Tit. 3.3. Rom. 3.12.</hi> And wee are ſo confirmed in this naturall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that wee can no more <hi>doe good, then an Ethiopian can change his skinne, or a Leopard his ſpots,</hi> Ierem 13.23. or, <hi>Then an evill Tree can bring foorth good fruite,</hi> Matth. 7.18. So that faith is Gods gift, <hi>Epheſ 2.8. Phil. 1.29.</hi> So is repentance, <hi>2. Tim. 2.25.</hi> So is the knowledge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly myſteries, <hi>Matth. 13.11.</hi> In a word, every thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2518:14"/>that is good in us, is from Gods ſpeciall grace, <hi>For wee are not ſufficient of our ſelves to thinke any thing as of our ſelves: but our ſufficiencie is of God,</hi> 2. Corinth 3.5. <hi>It is God that worketh in you both to will and to doe,</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>For who maketh thee to differ from another? And what haſt thou, that thou didſt not receive? 1. Cor. 4.7.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, thou differs much from others, who are not as yet converted; but it is not thy ſelfe that hath made this ſeparation, by the right uſe of thy owne free will, embracing that grace, which was equally offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto them: but it is God that wrought more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in thee, then in them: For God doth not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech us, by the Miniſtery of reconciliation; but alſo <hi>Hee powres upon us the ſpirit of grace,</hi> Zach. 12.10. <hi>Hee ſheds on us abundantly the holy ſpirit,</hi> Tit. 3.6. <hi>He workes powerfully in us,</hi> Epheſ-3. verſ. 20. So 2. Theſ. 1.11. Hee is ſaid to <hi>worke faith with power,</hi> and Epheſ. 1.19. It is called <hi>the exceeding greatneſſe of his power,</hi> and <hi>the working of his mightie power;</hi> and <hi>Coloſ. 2.12.</hi> This power in the converſion of a ſinner, is equalled to that whereby God raiſed up CHRIST from the dead. Our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (to expreſſe this powerfull working) cals our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion a <hi>drawing, No man can come to mee, except the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw him,</hi> Iohn 6.44. Hee doth indeede draw us; for of our ſelves wee are enemies to our owne ſalvation, and doe nothing elſe, but reſiſt the holy Ghoſt in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Word: yet hee who is able to doe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abundantly, above all that wee aske or thinke, overcommeth this reſiſtence in the will of man, and of unwilling, makes us willing:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> This is his Grace which never is in vaine; for <hi>all that the father giveth mee, ſhall come to mee,</hi> ſaith CHRIST, <hi>Iohn 6.37.</hi> It is alſo called a boring of the care, <hi>Pſal. 40.6.</hi> An opening of the heart,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2518:15"/>
               <hi>Act. 16.14.</hi> The Circumciſion of the heart, <hi>Deut. 30.6.</hi> And further to ſignifie not onely Gods powerfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in our converſion; but alſo our owne inabilitie to bring any helpe to this worke, it is called a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Epheſ</hi>3. 10. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3 <hi>Iam.</hi> 1 18 <hi>Epheſ</hi> 2.1 <hi>John,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> a regeneration, a vivification and reſurrection from the dead. A man cannot create himſelfe, nor beget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, no6r quicken himſelfe when bee is dead, Nay, hee cannot ſo much as bring anie helpe to theſe workes, but is meerely patient: So is hee in his converſion to God. Finally the worke of our converſion is called a renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heart, <hi>Ezech. 36.26. I will give you a new heart, and put a new ſpirit within you, I will take away the stonie heart, and give you a heart of fleſh, and I will put my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my Statutes.</hi> This is a promulgation of the Covenant of Grace; where yee may perceive the difference betweene this new Covenant, and the old. In the covenant of workes God required obedience to his law, and wee were unable to performe it. In the covenant of Grace, God requires faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and wee are as unable to performe that Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in then is the difference? Even in this, that the firſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant had no ſuch power annexed to it, to worke in us, that which it required from us; but in the new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that condition which God requireth from us, hee worketh in us. Hee cals us to returne, and hee turnes us. But then (will a Papiſt ſay) To what purpoſe are theſe exhortations? Doth God commaund us that which is impoſsible? And are his admonitions in vaine? I anſwer. Firſt, God commaunds us many things which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</note> not abſolutely, but as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>In aſmuch as the Law is weake, becauſe of the fleſh:</hi> For once God gave us a power to doe whatſoever hee commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and wee by our fall have loſt this power; yet hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2518:15"/>not God loſt his right to demaund that debt of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which his creature oweth unto him: So that the Commandements of God in this ſtate of corruption are the meaſure of our debt, not of our ſtrength; they ſhew us what wee ſhould doe, not what wee can doe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, neyther are theſe exhortations in vaine; for God doth not regenerate us by ſudden enthuſiaſmes; but by ordinary meanes: and theſe exhortations are the meanes, without which ordinarily no man is, or can bee conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Wee are begotten <hi>by the word of trueth.</hi> Iam. 1.18. <hi>Through the Goſpell, 1. Cor. 4.15.</hi> Of the incorruptible ſeede of the word, 1. <hi>Pet. 1.23.</hi> Now no man will ſay that it is in vaine to uſe ordinarie meanes, as to take meate for to nouriſh our bodies, Phyſicke to recover our health, to caſt ſeede in the ground, for to bring foorth fruite, though the event bee not in our power, but in Gods hands: So neyther can theſe exhortations to repentance be in vaine, though it bee not in our power to returne unto the Lord. Thirdly, theſe exhortations ſerve to humble us with a ſight of our owne inabilitie, and alſo to direct us what things wee are to aske of God by prayer: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of S. <hi>Auguſtine, Deus jubet aliqua,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De gratia &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> arbit. cap.</hi> 16.</note> quae non poſſumus; ut noverimus quid ab illo petere debeamus.</hi> God commaunds us ſome things which are not in our power, that wee might know what things wee have to aske of him by prayer. For when I heare that I am commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to returne unto the Lord, and yet looking upon mine owne ſtrength, I finde no ſuch power in my ſelfe; this muſt make mee goe out of my ſelfe, and flie unto the throne of Grace, crying (with the Spouſe of CHRIST) <hi>Draw mee, and I will runne after thee, Cant. 1.3.</hi> and (with <hi>Ephraim) Convert mee, and I ſhalbe converted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,18 <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51, 13.</note> and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid) create in me a cleane heart,</hi> and with the Diſciples, <hi>Lord
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2518:16"/>increaſe our faith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. August.</note> and with that holy Father, <hi>Domine, da, quod jubes, &amp; jube quod vis,</hi> Give mee a power to doe that which thou commaunds, and then commaund mee to doe what thou wilt. Finally, this precept is given unto us, becauſe there is ſomething in our power to doe, we can uſe the meanes, as goe to Church, and heare the word: Beſides after that God in the firſt moment of our upriſing, hath revived the heart, and given life to the dead will; then, <hi>acti agimus,</hi> Wee are no longer paſsive, but coworkers with God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31.19.</note> 
               <hi>After I was converted, I repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ephraim</hi>) Hence as our converſion is aſcribed to God, as the firſt and ſole Author, ſo it is aſcribed to our ſelves as inſtruments of God apprehending his grace, and working forward with it. God is ſaid to give faith, and wee are ſaid to beleeve: God is ſaid to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and wee are ſaid to repent: God is ſaid to turne us, and wee are ſaid to turne unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>From the exhortation, I come to the arguments: Indeede there is not a word in all the exhortation but it contaynes in it an argument to invite them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Firſt, <hi>O Iſrael,</hi> Thou that art Gods owne people, What ſhame is it for thee to turne thy backe upon God? Secondly, <hi>Returne,</hi> thou haſt gone aſtray, therefore come backe againe into the right way. Thirdly, <hi>unto the Lord,</hi> hee is IEHOVAH, the fountaine of all goodneſſe, that hath right unto thee by creation, by redemption, by covenant, by many other obligations: therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto him. Fourthly, he is <hi>thy God,</hi> and therefore if thou wilt returne unto him, hee will receive thee. Fiftly, <hi>Thou hast fallen by thine iniquitie,</hi> therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue no longer in that courſe which hath procured thy fall, leaſt thou periſh; but returne unto the Lord, that he may rayſe thee up. But the two laſt are the chiefe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2518:16"/>one whereof is taken from Gods mercie, hee is <hi>thy God:</hi> another from their owne miſcrie; <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, hee is <hi>thy God,</hi> thine by creation, thine by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, thine by adoption, thine by contract and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; for this is the covenant which hee made with <hi>Abraham</hi> thy father: <hi>I will bee a God unto thee,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 7.7.</note> and to thy ſeede after thee.</hi> Therefore thou may aſſure thy ſelfe, thy ſinne is pardonable, if thou wilt returne unto him, hee will imbrace thee in the armes of his mercie. Hence obſerue that the exhortations to repentance in Scripture, are founded commonly upon the mercie of God, as <hi>Iſai. Chap. 55.7. Let the wicked for ſake his way, and the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous his owne imaginations, and returne unto the Lord, and he will have mercie upon him, and to our God, for hee will abundantly pardon.</hi> In the Latin, it is, <hi>Multus ad igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendum:</hi> Whereupon (ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>) <hi>In hoc multo, nihil deeſt, ubi est omnipotens miſericordia, &amp; miſericors omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia:</hi> Hee can pardon, for his mercie is omnipotent; and hee will pardon, for his omnipotencie is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>Hoſ. 6.1. Come</hi> (ſay the repenting <hi>Iſraelits</hi>) <hi>let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto the Lord; for hee hath torne, and hee will heale us, hee hath ſmitten, and hee will bind us up.</hi> Ioel 2.13. <hi>Turne unto the Lord your God for he is gracious, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kindeneſſe, and repenteth him of the evill.</hi> And <hi>Ierem. 3.</hi> There bee many the like exhortations, all upon this ground, verſ. 12. <hi>Thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Iſrael returne, and I will not let my wrath fall upon you for I am mercifull, and will not alway keepe mine anger.</hi> Againe, verſ. 14. <hi>O yee diſobedient Children, turne againe, for I am your Lord.</hi> And after verſ. 22. <hi>O yee diſobedient children returne, and I will heale your rebellions.</hi> This is the argument uſed by the preacher of repentance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 35</note> 
               <hi>Repent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2518:17"/>for the kingdome of heaven is at hand,</hi> in which CHRIST is readie to diſpenſe mercie, and forgiveneſſe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting ſinner. So here, <hi>O Iſrael returne unto the Lord,</hi> for he is thy God, not, hee is a great, or a juſt, or a wiſe, or a powerfull God; but hee is <hi>thy God;</hi> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his exhortation upon Gods mercie. The reaſon is, becauſe a ſinner apprehending nothing but rigour and ſeveritie in God, will never come in and ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 130.4</note> No, <hi>There is mercie with thee O Lord that thou mayst bee feared.</hi> It is not the conſideration of Gods great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor of his power, nor of his juſtice, nor of his wiſedome, that can make the heart of a ſinner relent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him; but it is the conſideration of his mercie: when looking upon the mercy of God, and merits of CHRIST, I get ſome hope and inckling of pardon, then will I come in, creeping and crouching before God; as the <hi>Syrians</hi> to <hi>Achab,</hi> with ropes about their neckes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had <hi>heard that the Kings of Iſrael were mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi> The thundering out of the threatnings and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Law, will awake a ſecure heart; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will affect a mans minde, and even melt his ſoule to make him returne unto the Lord, but the due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſideration of the unſpeakeable riches of Gods mercie: The remembrance of his fathers houſe, made the heart of the prodigall to relent; So will the conſideration of Gods mercies worke upon our heart, if once our hearts be inflamed with the ſenſe of Gods love towards us, Oh then the working of our bowels! the ſtirring of our affections! the melting and relen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our repenting hearts! then will wee <hi>lament after the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1, Sam,</hi> 7, 2</note> and grieve that ever wee have ſo grieved ſo good and gracious a God. Therefore you ſee the wicked, that get a ſight of their ſinnes, becauſe they have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2518:17"/>not a ſight of Gods mercie, they runne away from God, as <hi>Adam,</hi> they are ſwallowed up of diſpaire as <hi>Cain,</hi> and never ſeeke after that mercie which they know not: But the Godly with the ſight of their ſinnes, having a ſenſe of Gods mercie, and a ſight of Gods face reconciled to them in IESVS CHRIST, How doe they ſeeke after that mercie with a longing deſire? Out of the deepes with <hi>David,</hi> and out of the belly of Hell with <hi>Ionas,</hi> they call upon God. Even when wounded by God, they goe to him to bee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as the repenting Iſraelites,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ,</hi> 6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> 
               <hi>Come let us returne unto the Lord, for hee hath wounded, and hee will heale us:</hi> and theſe converts that ſought for eaſe of him that pricked them, <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall wee doe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act,</hi> 2 37.</note> So that there is nothing in God ſo forceable to drive a man to repentace, as the conſideration of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. As <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid when hee pleaded before <hi>Caeſar</hi> for the life and libertie of <hi>Ligarius: O Caeſar, none of thy vertues is more gracious, or more admirable, then thy mercie: Men come neare to God in nothing ſo much as in ſaving the afflicted: Thy fortune hath nothing grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that thou hast power, thy nature nothing better then that thou haſt will to ſhew mercie, and to ſave others.</hi> So may I ſay among all the properties of the divine nature, there is none more admirable or more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then his mercie. It is not his power, it is not his wiſedome, it is not his juſtice wherein wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; but it is his mercie: If there were not mercie in God, I ſhould diſpaire, there is ſo much miſerie in mee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 12, 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> therefore <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the mercies of
God:</hi> I will not adjure you by the threatnings, but I beſeech you by the mercies of God, <hi>Knowing that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2518:18"/>the goodneſſe of God leadeth you to repentance;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 2, 4,</note> hee is thy God, and therefore <hi>O Iſrael returne unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other argument is taken from their ſenſe of miſerie, <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</hi> Our fals in Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam,</hi> 3, 2,</note> doe ſometimes ſignifie our ſinnes, <hi>In many things wee fall all</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi>) and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our afflictions, as in that place of <hi>Salomon, The juſt man falleth ſeven times a day:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prunb,</hi> 24, 16,</note> ſo heere it ſignifieth affliction, Thou haſt fallen, namely into danger and deſtruction; thou art afflicted, therefore returne. Where wee may obſerve, That our fals are many times an occaſion of our riſings, and afflictions are of excellent uſe to turne us to God: for this is the motive which the Prophet uſeth. Thou art fallen, therefore returne. And hardly could hee uſe a better; for affliction is a moſt effectuall meanes to make our hearts relent and reſolve into the teares of unſayned repentance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob,</hi> 33.16,</note> according to that of <hi>Elihu, God openeth the eares of men by their corrections, which hee had ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that hee might cauſe man to turne away from his purpoſe.</hi> So the Lord taught <hi>Miriam</hi> by leproſie to forgoe her murmuring. Hee awakened <hi>Ionas</hi> out of his ſecuritie, by caſting him into the Sea. Hee cured <hi>Zachary</hi> of infidelitie, by ſtriking him with dumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Hee diverted <hi>Saul</hi> from his evill courſe by blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thus <hi>Manaſſes</hi> (who forgat God in his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) did ſeeke unto him in adverſitie; the Heathen Marriners did pray unto God in a ſtorme; and the <hi>Ninevits</hi> did humble themſelves by faſting and prayer when deſtruction was threatened againſt them;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen,</hi> 42, 21,</note> when the brethren of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> were diſtreſſed in <hi>Egipt,</hi> they did remember the injurie they had done to their brother;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2518:18"/>when the prodigall ſonne was pinched with want,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 15, 18,</note> then did hee reſolve to returne to his father: but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially this may bee ſeene in the Iewiſh Church. For, though in their proſperitie (as the Lord himſelfe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth) <hi>They turned their backe yet in their trouble;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem,</hi> 2, 27,</note> they ſaid; Ariſe and helpe us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai,</hi> 26, 16,</note> This is obſerved alſo by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78, 34.</note> Lord in trouble have they viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee, they powred out a prayer when thy chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was upon them.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>When hee ſlew them, they ſought him:</hi> Yea (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the manifold kindes of miſerie wherewith the faithfull are exerciſed) hee maketh this the foote of his ſong, <hi>Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 81, 7, <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 107, 6,</note> and hee delivered them. Apollonius</hi> writes of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine people that could ſee nothing in the day, but all in the night: In like manner wee are ſo blinded with the bright ſunne-ſhine of proſperitie, that wee cannot ſee thoſe things which concerne our peace; but when the winter night of miſerie comes, then <hi>ſchola Crucis, ſchola lucis.</hi> Wee are all branches of the Vine, and therefore wee muſt bee pruned and cut with the knife of affliction that wee may bring forth fruite: and this is the laſt meanes which God ordinarily uſeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert obſtinate ſinners: when nothing can prevaile with us, then doth hee viſite our iniquities with the rod, and our ſinnes with ſcourges; and hee is ſo confident that this will drive vs to repentance, that in the fift Chapter of this propheſie, verſ. 15. (having threatened to withdraw all the teſtimonies of his love, and favour from his people, <hi>I will goe, and returne to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and ſeeke my face</hi>) Hee addes, <hi>In their affliction they will ſeeke me
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2518:19"/>carely:</hi> which was accordingly verified in the event; for in the next words they call one another after this manner, <hi>Come let us returne unto the Lord, for he hath vvounded us, &amp;c.</hi> And ſurely this is a ſtrange thing, that affliction ſhould make men turne to him that ſmiteth them; it would ſeeme that ſuch dealing ſhould rather terrific them, and make them runne away from God. <hi>Adam</hi> when hee ſaw God to bee angrie, fled from his preſence, and this is naturall to everie creature to love it ſelfe, and to flie from that which is hurtfull unto it: ſtrike a dogge, and hee will flic from you.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg,</hi> 14, 14,</note> Therefore that yee may conceive this riddle, how ſweere comes out of ſower: yee ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that afflictions being conſidered in their owne nature, are the fruites of ſinne, the evils of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the teſtimonies of Gods wrath, the curſes of the Law, and the firſt flaſhes of hels fire: Therefore when afflictions follow their kinde, they bring forth nothing but evill fruite, ſuch as impatiencie, malice againſt the inſtruments, murmuring againſt God, the uſe of unlawfull meanes,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 22,</note> and finally diſpaire, as in <hi>Pharao, Saul, Ierobeam, Achaz,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>in the time of his tribulation hee did yet treſpaſſe more against the Lord.</hi> But whenſoever afflictions doe drive a man to repentance, it is not properly of themſelves that they produce ſo good an effect, but by accident, as they are ſo diſpoſed by the infinite wiſedome, power, and goodneſſe of God, to whom onely it is proper to worke by contraries: hee brings light out of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, good out of evill; by ſinne hee condemned ſinne; by death hee deſtroyed death; by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching, hee makes us wiſe: hee caſts us downe that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2518:19"/>hee may rayſe us up; hee workes joy out of feare, heaven out of hell: and by the Croſſe which natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth baniſh a man from God, hee makes us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to him; hee cauſeth this birth and fruite of ſinne to kill the mother that brought it forth, this temporarie puniſhment to become a fatherly chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby wee are preſerved from the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhment of hels fire; theſe teſtimonies of his wrath, to become ſignes of his love, and ſeales of his adoption; and theſe curſes of the Law, and flaſhes of hell, to become Evangelicall bleſsings, and an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way whereby wee may travell toward his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kingdome. And therefore afflictions are fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the fire, which purifieth the gold, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth the ſtraw, and to the winde, which purgeth the Wheate, and bloweth away the Chaffe: and finally to the red Sea, which was to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> a way, to the <hi>Egiptians</hi> a grave. Now ſince afflictions produce ſo divers effects: wee muſt labour to have our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo ſanctified, as that wee may bee bettered by them. To this effect, Firſt when wee are under anie Croſſe, wee muſt labour after tender hearts, that wee may bee affected with griefe and paine: for there is not a greater enemie to our profitting by afflictions, then that ſenſeleſſe indolencie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whereby men are not affected with Gods judgements, like thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> of whom the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Thou haſt ſtricken them, but they have not ſorrowed:</hi> For, when afflictions being added to our ſinnes, as a double waight cannot bruſe our hearts, and preſſe out of them ſighes and groanes; it is not likely that ſinne alone will worke in them ſorrow and remorſe, but on the other part, if wee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2518:20"/>bee ſenſible of our afflictions, then this worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will make way for godly ſorrow, as a Needle doth for the threade. Secondly, let us remember that all the afflictions which doe befall us come from God: This is another lett that hindereth many from profitting by afflictions, even their blindneſſe, whereby they aſcribe all their calamities wholy to ſecondarie cauſes, and inferior meanes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos,</hi> 3, 6,</note> and never looke up to the hand of God ſtriking them, which is the chiefe cauſe; for <hi>there is no evill in the Citie which the Lord hath not done.</hi> Thirdly, let us looke backe into our former courſes, and ſee what wee have done againſt God; for hee would not ſtrike us without a cauſe: by this examination wee will come to a ſight and ſenſe of our ſinnes: wee will finde that wee have gone aſtray from God, and have fallen becauſe of our iniquitie. Finally, with the ſenſe of our ſinnes, let us ſtrive to get a ſight of Gods mercie revealed in the Goſpell, remembring that hee is our God: ſo will we deſire to returne to him.</p>
            <p>But the Prophet would not onely make them ſenſible of their fall, but alſo of their ſinne; therefore he illuſtrates this argument from the cauſe, <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie,</hi> or becauſe of thine iniquity. Here obſerve, That iniquitie procures a fall, ſo that if wee have fallen, then we have committed iniquitie; &amp; if we commit iniquitie, wee ſhall aſſuredly fall. I ſay, If wee have fallen, we may accuſe our iniquities which is the deſerving cauſe of all our afflictions The Apoſtle tels us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 5, 12,</note> that <hi>by ſinne death entred into the world,</hi> and if it had not beene for ſinne, death (whereby wee are to underſtand every thing that is penall and huttfull to the creature) could never have found an entrie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 3, 39</note> So the Church in the <hi>Lamentations,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2518:20"/>Wherefore is the living man ſorrowfull?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 107, 17,</note> Man ſuffereth for his ſinne:</hi> And the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Fooles by reaſon of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, and becauſe of their iniquities are afflicted.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouerb,</hi> 13, 21,</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> maketh affliction to bee (as it were) the ſhadow of ſinne which doth alway attend it, <hi>Affliction followeth ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverb,</hi> 22, 8,</note> and as our fals convince us to have committed iniquitie; ſo our iniquities forewarne us of a fall: For <hi>he that ſoweth iniquitie ſhall reape affliction.</hi> This doctrine is ſufficiently proved by Scripture, reaſon and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. God threatened <hi>Adam,</hi> that at what time hee did eate of the forbidden Tree, hee ſhould die. Everie ſinne unto man is the forbidden Tree, if wee meddle with it, wee ſhall finde no better fruite upon it then <hi>Adam</hi> found: the bitter fruite of death, growes upon the pleaſant Tree of ſinne: It is the ſentence of the law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 6, 23,</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is everie man that abideth not in all things that are written in the booke of the Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam,</hi> 1, 18.</note> This is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The reward of ſinne is death.</hi> And <hi>Iames, Sinne when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth death.</hi> Hee ſaith not, that every ſinne bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth death, but onely ſinne when it is fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or perfected, that is come to an height: for God in his mercie forgiveth ſinnes not finiſhed, or at leaſt hee tolerateth them, till they come to perfection, that the ſinner may bee without all excuſe: but in his juſtice, hee judgeth and condemneth ſinnes conſummate by hardneſſe of heart, and impenitencie, as hee ſheweth himſelfe, <hi>Amos 1.3. For three tranſgreſsions of Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, and for foure, I will not turne away the puniſhment thereof, &amp;c.</hi> As if hee had ſaid, if <hi>Damaſcus</hi> had ſinned onely once in perſecuting of my Church, I would turne away my judgments: but they have ſinned often, <hi>To three</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2518:21"/>bee ſenſible of our afflictions, then this worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will make way for godly ſorrow, as a Needle doth for the threade. Secondly, let us remember that all the afflictions which doe befall us come from God. This is another lett that hindereth many from profitting by afflictions, even their blindneſſe, whereby they aſcribe all their calamities wholy to ſecondarie cauſes, and inferior meanes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 3, 6,</note> and never looke up to the hand of God ſtriking them, which is the chiefe cauſe; for <hi>there is no evill in the Citie which the Lord hath not done.</hi> Thirdly, let us looke backe into our former courſes, and ſee what wee have done againſt God; for hee would not ſtrike us without a cauſe: by this examination wee will come to a ſight and ſenſe of our ſinnes: wee will finde that wee have gone aſtray from God, and have fallen becauſe of our iniquitie. Finally, with the ſenſe of our ſinnes, let us ſtrive to get a fight of Gods mercie revealed in the Goſpell, remembring that hee is our God: ſo will we deſire to returne to him.</p>
            <p>But the Prophet would not onely make them ſenſible of their fall, but alſo of their ſinne; therefore he illuſtrates this argument from the cauſe, <hi>Thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie,</hi> or becauſe of thine iniquity. Here obſerve, That iniquitie procures a fall, ſo that if wee have fallen, then we have committed iniquitie; &amp; if we commit iniquitie, wee ſhall aſſuredly fall. I ſay, If wee have fallen, we may accuſe our iniquities which is the deſerving cauſe of all our afflictionss<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Apostle tels us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 5, 12,</note> that <hi>by ſinne death entred into the world,</hi> and if it had not beene for ſinne, death (whereby wee are to underſtand every thing that is penall and huttfull to the creature) could never have found an entrie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam,</hi> 1, 39</note> So the Church in the <hi>Lamentations,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2518:21"/>Wherefore is the living man ſorrowfull?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 107, 17,</note> Man ſuffereth for his ſinne:</hi> And the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Fooles by reaſon of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, and becauſe of their iniquities are afflicted.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouerb,</hi> 13, 21,</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> maketh affliction to bee (as it were) the ſhadow of ſinne which doth alway attend it, <hi>Affliction followeth ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proverb,</hi> 22, 8,</note> and as our fals convince us to have committed iniquitie; ſo our iniquities forewarne us of a fall: For <hi>he that ſoweth iniquitie ſhall reape affliction.</hi> This doctrine is ſufficiently proved by Scripture, reaſon and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. God threatened <hi>Adam,</hi> that at what time hee did eate of the forbidden Tree, hee ſhould die. Everie ſinne unto man is the forbidden Tree, if wee meddle with it, wee ſhall finde no better fruite upon it then <hi>Adam</hi> found: the bitter fruite of death, growes upon the pleaſant Tree of ſinne: It is the ſentence of the law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 6, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is everie man that abideth not in all things that are written in the booke of the Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam,</hi> 1, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> This is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The reward of ſinne is death.</hi> And <hi>Iames, Sinne when it is finiſhed, bringeth forth death.</hi> Hee ſaith not, that every ſinne bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth death, but onely ſinne when it is fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or perfected, that is come to an height: for God in his mercie forgiveth ſinnes not finiſhed, or at leaſt hee tolerateth them, till they come to perfection, that the ſinner may bee without all excuſe: but in his juſtice, hee judgeth and condemneth ſinnes conſummate by hardneſſe of heart, and impenitencie, as hee ſheweth himſelfe, <hi>Amos</hi> 1.3. <hi>For three tranſgreſsions of Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, and for foure, I will not turne away the puniſhment thereof, &amp;c.</hi> As if hee had ſaid, if <hi>Damaſcus</hi> had ſinned onely once in perſecuting of my Church, I would turne away my judgments: but they have ſinned often, <hi>To three
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2518:22"/>tranſgreſsions, they have added foure, they have threſhed Gilead, with threſhing instruments of Iron,</hi> and for ſo many tranſgreſsions I will not turne away their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Againe of ſinne finiſhed it is not ſaid, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth death, which is common to all ſinne; but that it bringeth forth death, where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth to bee delivered of that which hath beene concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. So that ſinne when once it commeth to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is with childe of death, and muſt needes bee delivered. When Gods patience is abuſed, it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come futie, when the cup of Gods wrath is full, it muſt of neceſsitie runne over; when the meaſure of our iniquities is fulfilled, then muſt God powre forth the vials of his wrath:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 5, 5</note> And great reaſon there is why it muſt bee ſo, if wee conſider the juſtice of God, the nature of ſinne, and the trueth of Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The juſtice of God is ſuch, that hee hateth ſinne;
<note place="margin">2, <hi>Theſ,</hi> 2, 6</note> and therefore will hee puniſh it. <hi>The fooliſh ſhall not stand in thy ſight,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>for thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test all them that worke iniquitie,</hi> reaſoning from the nature of God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 2, 32</note> God hateth iniquitie, therefore hee will puniſh it. And the Apoſtle, <hi>It is a just thing with God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ,</hi> 18, 20</note> to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you.</hi> This is the juſtice of God (which even the <hi>Gentils</hi> knew) <hi>that they who commit ſuch things are worthie of death.</hi> Againe the nature of ſinne is to crie, <hi>The cry of Sodome is great:</hi> It crieth, citing us before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall of God, as guiltie of leaſe Majeſtie; it cryeth unto the heavens for vengeance; provoking God to revenge, and not ſuffering him to reſt in heaven till hee hath inflicted puniſhment. Finally Gods truth is ſuch that none of his threatenings can fall to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2518:22"/>ground; but hee hath threatened a fall to iniquitie, and according to his threatening, hath hee executed his wrath upon impenitent ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When the earth was filled with violence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ,</hi> 6, 13</note> then God ſent the floud upon the olde world. When the crie of <hi>Sodome</hi> waxed great before God, then ſent hee Angels to deſtroy it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ</hi> 19 15. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.16 1. <hi>King</hi> 21 20.</note> When the iniquitie of the <hi>Amorites</hi> was full, then were they caſt forth. When <hi>Achab</hi> ſold himſelfe to worke evill in the ſight of the Lord, then did the Lord bring evill upon him: When <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> filled up the meaſure of their fathers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math,</hi> 23, 32,</note> then they could not eſcape the damnation of hell. When the ſinnes of <hi>Babell</hi> are come to that height,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 18, 5.</note> that they reach unto the heaven, then will the Lord remember her iniquities. Goe and enquire, what is become of thoſe famous Churches planted by the Apoſtles, of <hi>Corinth, Epheſus, Galatia, &amp;c.</hi> Are they not fallen by their iniquitie? What is become of Gods owne people, the <hi>Iewes?</hi> They are fallen, and that by their iniquitie (as the Lord himſelfe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) <hi>Iſaiah, 50.1.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 49. 12.</note> Behold for your iniquities are yee ſold, and becauſe of your tranſgreſsions is your Mother forſaken.</hi> Now if God ſpared not them: How will hee ſpare us? I may ſay unto you (as the Lord doth to <hi>Idumea</hi>) <hi>Behold they whoſe judgement was not to drinke of the cup,</hi> (that is, they that were mine owne people, and had not ſo much deſerved pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as thou) <hi>have aſſuredly drunken, and art thou hee that ſhall goe unpuniſhed, thou ſhalt not goe unpuniſhed, but thou ſhalt ſurely drinke of it.</hi> If once our iniquities are come to the height,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2518:23"/>then wee ſhall fall as they have fallen. Now ſinnes of a Nation are finiſhed, and come to the height, when they are generall, when they are not puniſhed, and when they are perſevered in, men continuing in their ſinnes without repentance. Firſt (I ſay) when they are generall; for ſo long as there bee onely ſome wicked men in a kingdome, their ſinnes are perſonall, and cannot bring the judgements of God upon the whole land; for tenne righteous men God would have ſpared <hi>Sodome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6.12.</note> but if ſinne become generall, <hi>That all fleſh hath corrupted his way upon the earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 19.4,</note> then will the deluge bee univerſall likewiſe. <hi>If all the men of Sodome, from the young to the old, even all the people from all quarters,</hi> conſpire to commit filthineſſe: then ſhall the whole Citie be overthrowne. Sinne was come to this height in <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 1, 5,</note> for (ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) <hi>The whole head is ſicke, &amp; the whole heart heavie. From the ſole of the foote unto the head, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whole therein, but wounds and ſwelling, and ſores full of corruption. A conſpiracie</hi> (ſaith the Lord himſelfe) <hi>is found among the men of Iudah, and among the inhabitants of Ieruſalem,</hi> Ierem. 11.9. For why? <hi>The children of Iſrael, and the children of Iudah did evill, even they, their Kings, their Princes, their Prieſts, and their Prophets, the men of Iudah, and the inhabitants of Ieruſalem,</hi> Ierem. 32.32. In ſo much that the Lord ſaith to the Prophet: <hi>Runne to and fro by the streetes of Ieruſalem, and behold now, and know, and enquire in the open places thereof, if yee can finde a man, or if there bee any that executeth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſeeketh the truth, and I will ſpare it, Ierem.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2518:23"/>5.1.</hi> This generall revolt from God, is expreſſed by this Prophet in the fourth Chapter: <hi>The Lord hath a controverſie with the land, becauſe there is no trueth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the land, &amp;c.</hi> This was a generall, and ſo a nationall ſinne: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the puniſhment generall upon the Nation likewiſe. verſ. 3. <hi>The land ſhall mourne, and everie one that dwelleth therein ſhall bee cut off.</hi> Secondly, The ſinnes of a Nation are come to an height, when they are not puniſhed by the Magiſtrate, but all goe on in their courſes without controlment.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 25 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> When <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſmote the adulterous perſons, hee turned Gods anger away from the children of Iſrael, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the plague to ceaſe: but where there is not a <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> to draw the ſword for the puniſhment of vice, there the guilt of theſe ſinnes lye upon the land, and draw downe the judgements of God upon a Nation. In this caſe was <hi>Iſrael</hi> before her captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for this is expreſſed as a cauſe of their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>They execute no judgement, Ierem. 5.28.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 1.23.</note> But (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>Their Princes were rebellious and companions of theeves; everie one loved gifts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chapt.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 4.11, <hi>Chapt.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25.</note> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after rewards. Children were their Princes, and women had rule over them; they did juſtifie the wicked for reward.</hi> A third degree of perfection in ſinne is perſeverance. When men continue in ſinne without repentance, hardening their hearts againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was come to this height alſo: <hi>For the Lord ſent unto them all his ſervants the Prophets, riſing up earely, and ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 35.15.</note> returne now every man from his evill way, and amend your workes: — but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2518:24"/>they would not incline their eare, nor obey;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon came their fall: for it followeth in the Text. verſ. 17. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord of hostes, behold I will bring upon Iudah, and upon all the inhabitants of Ieruſalem, all the evill that I have pronounced againſt them, becauſe I have ſpoken unto them, but they would not heare.</hi> Now let us examine our ſelves, and ſee whether wee bee come to ſuch an height of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and I doubt we ſhall finde, Firſt that ſinne raigneth univerſally, like an Epidemicall diſeaſe that poſſeſſeth the whole bodie of the land. There is in great men, facriledge and oppreſsion; in officers, briberie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, and wreſting of juſtice: In the cleargie, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, lazineſſe, and covetouſneſſe: In tradeſmen, fraude and deceite: In every corner Idolatrie, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, and ſhedding of bloud: and What houſe is free from adulterie, drunkenneſſe, and ſwearing? Next, doe but conſider whether theſe (and many moe ſinnes) bee committed ſafely, without puniſhment. Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſacriledge, have greatneſſe for their patron: injuſtice, briberie, and extortion, finde Lawyers to pleade their cauſe: Idolatrie is but a ſinne of tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De gubern. Dei lib,</hi> 5.</note> inceſt and uſurie are veniall in poore men, and venall in the rich: pride, ſwearing, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and gluttonie, are commendable becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as <hi>Salvianus</hi> complayned in his time, <hi>In hoc ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus res devoluta, ut niſi quis malus fuerit, ſalvus eſſe non poſsit.</hi> In plaine Engliſh, except a man be thus wicked, hee cannot bee reputed a good fellow. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly robberie &amp; parricide, doe ſometimes finde pardon And laſtly, Doe wee not perſevere in theſe ſinnes, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2518:24"/>fall away more and more, hardening out hearts againſt all admonitions? How then can wee eſcape a fall? Yea, have wee not fallen alreadie? Conſider but the eſtate of the reformed Churches, how in their infancie, when they were deſtitute of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, and all Princes and Potentates enemies unto them; yet then they did ſtand, maugre Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and all his aſſociats; Gods protection was a wall of defence about them, that the furie of their enemies could not come neere them; and now when they were growne great in the eyes of the world, and Kings were become their nurſing fathers, and Queenes their nurſing mothers, to protect Religion with the ſword: yet How hath the Lord humbled them, and made them to fall before their enemies?
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 1.5.2</note> The reaſon hereof wee finde in that ſpeech of <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prophet, to King <hi>Aſa, The Lord is with you, while yee are with him: but if yee for ſake him, he will forſake you:</hi> At firſt wee was with the Lord, and then hee was with us: but when we did forſake the Lord, &amp; fall from our firſt love, and zeale of our profeſsion; then did he breake downe the hedges,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80. 12</note> and let in the wilde Bore out of the wood, and the wilde beaſt out of the forreſt to deſtroy this Vine which he had planted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.42,</note> that wee may lament with <hi>Ieremie: Wee have ſinned, and have rebelled, therefore thou hast not ſpared.</hi> Thus hath God made us to fall: but unleſſe wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto him, there is yet a greater fall to come. The ſame God that made <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a ſcourge to his people; can ſend the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to ſcourge us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cedreu. hist. pag,</hi> 512.</note> When <hi>Phocas</hi> had built a mighty wall about his Pallace, for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2518:25"/>his ſecuritie, in the night hee heard a voyce: O King though thou build as high as the clouds, yet the Citie will eaſily be taken, the ſin within will marre all. So let us never make ſo much preparation for our defence:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 57.</note> yet unleſſe we take a courſe with our ſinnes, they will betray us into the hands of our enemies: For, (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>) <hi>Graviores ſunt inimici, mores pravi, quam hoſtes infesti.</hi> Our ſinnes, are enemies more to be feared then armed men. If God be with us, Who can bee againſt us? If wee ſtand againſt God, Who can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him?</p>
            <p>Now to ſhut up all in a word: It is plaine that wee have gone aſtray as farre as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did; for, what is the vanitie after which wee have not gone a whoring? and now our iniquities are come to that height,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ion.</hi> 3 8. 9.</note> that they forewarne us of a fall: <hi>Therefore let every man turne from his evill way, and from the wickedneſſe in their hand. Who can tell if God will turne &amp; repent and turne away from his fierce wrath, that wee periſh not?</hi> Yea, I can tell, that if wee repent, hee will turne away his wrath;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 55, 6.</note> for he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, and even now when the Axe is layd to the roote of the Tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> hee cals us to repentance. Therefore <hi>ſeeke the Lord while hee may bee found, call upon him while hee is neere;</hi> take up the reſolution of repenting <hi>Iſrael, I will goe and returne to my first husband; for then it was better with me then now:</hi> follow the counſell of the Prophet, in the words following my Text. <hi>Take with you words, and turne to the Lord, ſay unto him, Take away all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and receive us gratiouſly, ſo will wee render the calves of our lips. Aſhur ſhall not ſave us, wee will not ride
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2518:25"/>upon horſes, neyther will wee ſay any more to the worke of our hands, yee are our Gods; for in thee the fatherleſſe findeth mercie.</hi> Hee is our God, and therefore if wee ſeeke him, hee will bee found of us; and as hee hath wounded us, ſo hee will heale us; hee will even give us beautie for aſhes, and the oyle of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe, and make the bones which he hath broken to rejoyce. To this God, even our God, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA ſic CORRIGE.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle Dedicatory, <hi>l.</hi> 8. for yea, <hi>reade</hi> I, <hi>l.</hi> 13, for our <hi>reade</hi> an, <hi>l.</hi> 30 for profeſſor, <hi>reade</hi> protector, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 12 for heale, <hi>reade</hi> healed, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 16 for occaſion <hi>reade</hi> reaſon, <hi>p.</hi> 10 <hi>l.</hi> 17. for thus, <hi>reade</hi> this, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l</hi> 39 for was to come, <hi>reade</hi> was come.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
